Guide to the Geller and allied families papers, 1896-2022 MS 0768
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Geller and allied families papers
1896-2022
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Schwartz, Shari Swiff; Rubin, Devora Geller; Geller, Jacob; Geller, Jay; Zwick, Sharan Leff; Leff, Alicia D.; Katzeff, Harriet; Geller, Harriet
MS 0768
2.50 Linear Feet 4 boxes
This collection contains photographs, clippings, correspondence, and newsletters related to members of the Geller and Leff families from 1896 to 2022.
Geller Family
Jacob Geller was born, 1863, in what historically was known as Gilicia or Austrian Poland, which at the time of his birth was ruled as part of the Austrian Empire. His wife, Sara Wittis Geller, was also born in 1863 in Austrian Poland. The two were married in 1882. Rabbi Jacob Geller and his wife, Sara, immigrated to the United States from Europe around 1882 at the bequest of the Orthodox community of Galveston, Texas, to fulfill their search for an Orthodox rabbi. He served as rabbi for the congregation called "Bikur Cholim" for a number of years. While there he organized the Hebrew Orthodox Benevolent Association and dedicated a synagogue built by the Young Men's Hebrew Association. He served there for eighteen years, coming to Houston in 1910 to serve as rabbi of the Adath Israel congregation. He was elected for life tenure in November of 1929. He died February 10, 1930.
Jacob and Sara Geller had eight children: Harry Geller (1882-1963), Samuel Geller (1886-1971), Annie Geller Leff (1894-1973), Rabbi Max Geller (1896-1966), Abram L. Geller (1898-1989), Goldie Geller Minkes (1902-1986), and Gladys Leah Geller Gordon (1904-1982), and Esther Geller Rothkop (1907-1999).
Rabbi Max Geller was born May 27, 1896 in Galveston County, Texas and served as the rabbi of Congregation Beth Jacob for a number of years. In 1934, he was unanimously re-elected by Congregation Adath Israel to serve as spiritual leader for a period of ten years. The first native Texan to become an orthodox Jewish minister, Rabbi Geller was also active in civic and philanthropic affairs of the community. He died on July 11, 1966 at 70 years of age.
Abram L. Geller was born in Galveston, Texas on July 18, 1898. He was the son of Rabbi Jacob and Sara Geller. He graduated from Rice Institute in 1920. He worked for Leff Brothers Dry Goods Company. In 1923 he married Lebby Yellen of Beaumont, Texas. He had three children: Reba Geller Swiff, Devora Geller Rubin, Jacob Geller, and Golda Geller Baker. Geller belonged to the B'nai B'rith for 64 years and was a Zionist from the age of 22. He was past president of three synagues and a founder of Houston's Hebrew Academy. He helped organize Beth Jacob Congregation in 1937 with his brother Rabbi Max Geller. He died aged 90 on May 8, 1989.
Leff Family
The Leff brothers -- Ben, Jacob, and Sol -- were born in 1894, 1896 and 1900, respectively. The family immigrated from Austria to the United States in the early 1900s and settled in Texas. The three set up a corporation in 1921 and began a whole sale dry goods operation at 521 Preston Avenue in Houston. Sol was the salesman for South Texas, Jacob was office manager and sales, and Ben was buyer of all merchandise. After flooding twice the brothers moved the operation in 1937 to 1711 Preston. As the years passed the brothers' children began working in the family business, including Jacob's son David. Jacob Leff married Annie Geller (daughter of Rabbi Jacob and Sara Geller) in 1917. The couple had three children, including David M. Leff, born in Houston on August 24, 1924. David graduated from high school early and enrolled at Texas A&M University. David left college after three years, when World War II began, to join the Army where he served at military intelligence schools in France and England during the war. After the war, he returned to Texas A&M and graduated with a degree in business and accounting before joining his father and uncles at Leff Bros. Dry Goods. David met Evelyn Zimmerman on a blind date and the two married in 1947. They had three children: Stanley, Sharan, and Tina. Evelyn died in 1993 and David died in 2017 at the age of 93. Excerpted from: http://jhvonline.com/david-mendel-leff-p23495-124.htm
Scope and Contents
This collection contains four boxes of photographs, clippings, correspondence, and newsletters related to members of the Geller and Leff families spanning 1896 to 2022.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research. Stored off-site at the Library Service Center and requires 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were donated between 2018 and 2023 by members of the Geller and Leff families. For more information about the donations please see the accession records in this finding aid.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection consist of items donated by multiple family mambers. They have remained grouped with items in each individual donation and arranged in seven series as follows:
Series I: Harriet Katzeff - Geller Family Materials; Series II: Jay Geller materials; Series III: Norma Geller materials; Series IV: Jacob Geller papers; Series V: Geller/Leff Family; Series VI: Alicia Leff papers; Series VII: David M. Leff papers; Series VIII: Harriet Geller papers; Series IX: Oversize
Addendum materials that came in later are described in the finding aid with previous materials donated by the donor, but may not be in the same box as the original accession.
Related Materials
Mazkeres ahavah = Remembrance of love: a biographical account of Rabbi Yaakov and Sara Geller and family: the transplanting of Jewish life from Galicia to Texas 1863 to the present / by Shmuel Geller.https://onesearch.library.rice.edu/permalink/01RICE_INST/11atd6j/alma991033264762905251
Index Terms
Subjects
Jews and Jewish life
Document Types
photographs; newsletters; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.)
Subjects (Persons)
Geller, Jacob, Rabbi; Geller, Max, Rabbi
Subjects (Corporations)
Congregation Adath Israel (Houston, Tex.)
- Series I: Harriet Katzeff - Geller Family Materials, 1919-1988
  - United Jewish Appeal, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Family Members (4), 1919; 1930; 1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Rabbi Jacob Geller (2), 1931 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Adath Israel Cemetery, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Geller Family Home, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Rabbi Max Geller Photos (4), 1953-1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: Jay Geller materials, 1918-1935
  Scope and Contents
  The Jay Geller family papers contain black-and-white photographs of family members related to Jay Geller, including his father Isaac Meyer, aunts Leah Ramati and Shifra Ben-Zvi, great-uncles Rabbi Max Geller and Sam Geller (the latter married to Rose Geller), and his great-great-grandfather Rabbi Jacob Geller. A family tree depicting the relationships between family members in the collection can be found in the control folder.
  - Group photograph of Isaac Meyer Geller (b. 1905), Shifra Ben-Zvi Geller (b. 1914), Leah Ramati Geller (b.1907), and Sara Wittes Geller, ca. October 1918 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Portrait of Leah Geller, ca. 1925 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Portrait of Shifra Ben-Zvi Geller, addressed "To Uncle Sam and Aunt Rose with love from Shifra", June, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Group photograph of Harry Geller and Rabbi Max Geller in New York, July 4th, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photo of Harry Geller, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photograph of an unidentified man driving a car, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photograph of unidentified man (same as one driving car) with unidentified woman (Shifra?), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series III: Norma Geller materials
  - Dedication of the B'nai Zion Educational Building program, 1960-12-18 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Geller family history (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Samuel Geller's materials, 1916-1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Henry Geller's high school / college materials, 1936-1940 (Box 2)
  - Henry Geller's materials, 1940-2022 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Geller Family Correspondence (1 of 2), 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Geller Family Correspondence (2 of 2), 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Samuel Geller's College of the City of New York diploma, 1911-06-22 (Map-drawer 237, Folder 4)
  - Samuel Geller's Notary Public certificate, 1922-01-04 (Map-drawer 237, Folder 4)
- Series IV: Jacob Geller papers, 1944-1989
  Biographical / Historical
  Abram L. Geller was born in Galveston, Texas on July 18, 1898. He was the son of Rabbi Jacob and Sara Geller. He graduated from Rice Institute in 1920. He worked for Leff Brothers Dry Goods Company. In 1923 he married Lebby Yellen of Beaumont, Texas. He had three children: Reba Geller Swiff, Devora Geller Rubin, Jacob Geller, and Golda Geller Baker. Geller belonged to the B'nai B'rith for 64 years and was a Zionist from the age of 22. He was past president of three synagues and a founder of Houston's Hebrew Academy. He helped organize Beth Jacob Congregation in 1937 with his brother Rabbi Max Geller. He died aged 90 on May 8, 1989.
  Jacob Geller was born on May 30, 1930, the only son of Abram and Libby Geller. He attended Rice University and Baylor Dental School in Dallas, Texas. He served in the armed forces in the Air Force and Navy. He died on March 6, 2022.
  - Group photograph of National Convention, Zionist Organization of America, Atlantic City, NJ, 1944-10-15 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - News clippings about Abram Geller and Jacob Geller, ca. 1980s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Abram Geller biographical information (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Membership letter from Joyce Gilbert, President of Houston Action for Soviet Jewry, 1987-08 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Program, Reception honoring Abram and Libby Geller, 1978-12 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series V: Geller/Leff Family, 1910-1980
  Donor of the materials, Devora Geller Rubin is from a self-proclaimed "Rice Family." She attended Rice her freshman year at 16 before going on to complete her schooling at UT Austin in 1948. Devora's father, Abram Lewis Geller, graduated in the fourth class of the Rice Institute in 1920. Her husband and Dallas native, Louis Rubin, graduated from Rice in 1948, the same year as her cousin, Henry Geller. In addition, Rubin's aunts Florence Kless Yellen and Beulah Axelrod Yellen, uncle Milton Yellen, and brother Jacob Geller all attended Rice.
  In addition to its Rice connections, Rubin's family also has close ties to the Houston Jewish community. Her Grandfather, Rabbi Jacob Geller was rabbi of the Adath Israel congregation from 1910 until his passing, while her uncle, Rabbi Max Geller was the head of congregation Beth Jacob for a number of years. Rubin herself spent much of her youth in and around Beth Jacob, attending school across the street at Albert Sidney Johnson Junior High School.
  Rabbi Jacob Geller was born in Galicia and received his rabbinical training there, becoming rabbi of the orthodox community of Galveston in 1892. While there he organized the Hebrew Orthodox Benevolent Association and dedicated a synagogue built by the Young Men's Hebrew Association. He served there for eighteen years, coming to Houston in 1910 to serve as rabbi of the Adath Israel congregation. He was elected for life tenure in November of 1929. He died February 10, 1930 at 67 years of age, survived by his wife Mrs. Sara Geller, eight children: Harry Geller, Samuel Geller, Abram L. Geller, Rabbi Max Geller, Mrs. Jacob Leff and Miss Esther Geller, Mrs. Goldie Minkes, and Mrs. Leah Gordon.
  Rabbi Max Geller was born May 27, 1896 in Galveston County, Texas and served as the rabbi of congregation Beth Jacob for a number of years. In 1934, he was unanimously re-elected by the Congregation Adath Israel to serve as spiritual leader for a period of ten years. The first native Texan to become an orthodox Jewish minister, Rabbi Geller was also active in civic and philanthropic affairs of the community. He died on July 11, 1966 at 70 years of age.
  - Jewish Women in Houston Photograph, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - B'nai B'rith Youth Baseball & Basketball Team Photos (2), 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Party at Beth Jacob? Photograph, ca. early 1980s (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Congregation Beth Jacob 8th Annual Confirmation Exercises Program, June 6,1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Tau Beta Pi emblem, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Louis Rubin, Rice Institute grades, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Jewish Herald Voice news clipping, 1982-06-17 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - A.Z.A. group photograph - C.A. Installation Banquet, 1946-06-13 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - A.Z.A. group photograph - C.A. Installation Banquest, 1945-01-21 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Group photograph at Plantation, 1946-02-27 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Group photograph - C.A. picnic, Liondell Park, 1944-08-16 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series VI: Alicia Leff papers
  - Rabbi Jacob Geller framed portrait
  - News clippings, 1956-2000 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Seven Acres 50th annual meeting program, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Haddasah bulletins, 1973-1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Houston Haddasah messsge from the president, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The Message newsletter, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Seven Acres newsletter, 1981-2003 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series VII: David M. Leff papers
  The Leff brothers -- Ben, Jacob, and Sol -- were born in 1894, 1896 and 1900, respectively. The family immigrated from Austria to the United States in the early 1900s and settled in Texas. The three set up a corporation in 1921 and began a whole sale dry goods operation at 521 Preston Avenue in Houston. Sol was the salesman for South Texas, Jacob was office manager and sales, and Ben was buyer of all merchandise. After flooding twice the brothers moved the operation in 1937 to 1711 Preston. As the years passed the brothers' children began working in the family business, including Jacob's son David.
  Jacob Leff married Annie Geller (daughter of Rabbi Jacob and Sara Geller) in 1917. The couple had three children, including David M. Leff, born in Houston on August 24, 1924. David graduated from high school early and enrolled at Texas A&M University. David left college after three years, when World War II began, to join the Army where he served at military intelligence schools in France and England during the war. After the war, he returned to Texas A& M and graduated with a degree in business and accounting before joining his father and uncles at Leff Bros. Dry Goods. David met Evelyn Zimmerman on a blind date and the two married in 1947. They had three children: Stanley, Sharan, and Tina. Evelyn died in 1993 and David died in 2017 at the age of 93.
  Excerpted from: http://jhvonline.com/david-mendel-leff-p23495-124.htm
  - Family history correspondence, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Military Records of David M. Leff, 1943-1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - News clippings, Zimmerman/Leff engagement and marriage (2), 1947 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Leff Brothers Dry Goods and Notions Company 50th Anniversary book, 1921-1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Family photographs (10), 1945-1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series VIII: Harriet Geller Papers
  - Framed, handwritten Ketubah marriage certificate for Dr. Henry Geller and Harriet Lerner, 1958 (Map-drawer 237, Folder 4)
- Series IX: Oversize
  - Group photograph of Sara Geller surrounded by her children and grandchildren, including Max and Harry Geller, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Jewish Colonial Trust certificate, 1900-06-01 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Samuel Geller's Galveston High School diploma, 1906-06-15 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Marriage certificate for Samuel Geller and Rose Kerner, 1916-11-30 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Original and corrected naturalization papers for Jacob Geller, October 28, 1896 and July 5, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Henry Charles Geller's Congregation Beth El High School diploma, 1940-06-11 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Henry Geller's Certificate of Confirmation - Beth El, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 2)